Guide to the Frederick Edwards Papers, 1883-1945 RL.10150
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frederick Edwards papers
1883-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edwards, Frederick, 1863-1948.
RL.10150
10 Linear Feet 292 items
Frederick Edwards was an Episcopal clergyman and president of the American Society for Psychical Research. Collection contains correspondence, journal (1884-1945, 52 v.), sermons, meditations, and poems, chiefly relating to psychical phenomena and Edwards' views on theology and spiritualism, particularly life after death. Also includes letters, 1933-1935, commenting on Franklin Roosevelt, the New Deal, and the social effects of the Depression. Includes World War I letters and also poetry of Edwards' son, Frederick Trevenen, who died during the war.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frederick Edwards Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1956-1958.
Biographical Note
Episcopal clergyman and president of the American Society for Psychical Research.
Collection Overview
The principal part of this collection is made up of the journals kept by Frederick C. Edwards between 1884 and 1945 reflecting Edwards's career as an Episcopal minister and his study of psychical phenomena, especially life after death. They contain letters, sermons, nature essays, book orders, and some clippings and financial records with numerous entries for 1933-1935 commenting on Franklin Roosevelt, the New Deal, and the effects of the Depression on the people Edwards saw and knew; and a considerable amount of material concerning Edwards's interest in spiritualism and psychical research, including mention of sittings with various mediums and a few transcriptions of these sittings. The unbound letters are those of Edwards's son, Frederick Trevenen Edwards, describing his experiences in World War I. There is a typed copy of these letters emended by Edwards, and they were published in 1954 by Elizabeth Satterthwait The collection also contains assorted volumes and notebooks including Trevenen Edwards's poetry and prose and Frederick Edwards's nature poems.
Collection Arrangement
Volumes 1-58 are bound and unboxed, while volumes 59-61 are located in boxes 1-9.
Related Material
Frederick Trevenen Edwards' letters published in Fort Sheridan to Monfaucon: the war letters of Frederick Trevenen Edwards (1954), Elizabeth Satterthwait, ed.
World War, 1914-1918; Spiritualism; Soldiers -- Correspondence; New Deal, 1933-1939; Future life -- Episcopal Church; Depressions -- 1929; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; United States -- Economic policy -- 1933-1945; Episcopal Church -- Clergy; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Edwards, Frederick, 1863-1948.; Edwards, Frederick Trevenen
- Frederick Edwards Papers, 1883-1945, 79 volumes, 9 boxes
  Arrangement note
  Volumes 1-58 are bound and unboxed. Volumes 59-79 are housed in boxes 1-9.
  - Baptism, January 1-9 (Volume 1)
  - January 10-12 (Volume 2)
  - Disciples, January 13-18 (Volume 3)
  - January, January 25-February 6 (Volume 4)
  - February, February 7-12 (Volume 5)
  - February, February 13-18 (Volume 6)
  - Septuagesima, February 19-24 (Volume 7)
  - February 25-29 (Volume 8)
  - March, March 1-6 (Volume 9)
  - Lent, March 7-12 (Volume 10)
  - Lent, March 13-18 (Volume 11)
  - March, March 19-24 (Volume 12)
  - Perea, March 25-31 (Volume 13)
  - April, April 1-6 (Volume 14)
  - Palm Sunday, April 7-12 (Volume 15)
  - Good Friday, April 13-18 (Volume 16)
  - Easter, April 19-28 (Volume 17)
  - April 28-30 (Volume 18)
  - May, May 1-6 (Volume 19)
  - May, May 7-12 (Volume 20)
  - May, May 13-18 (Volume 21)
  - Ascension, May 19-31 (Volume 22)
  - June, June 1-6 (Volume 23)
  - Trinity, June 7-18 (Volume 24)
  - June, June 19-30 (Volume 25)
  - The Nation, July 1-6 (Volume 26)
  - July, July 7-12 (Volume 27)
  - July, July 13-18 (Volume 28)
  - July, July 19-24 (Volume 29)
  - July, July 25-31 (Volume 30)
  - Transfiguration, August 1-6 (Volume 31)
  - August, August 7-18 (Volume 32)
  - August, August 19-30 (Volume 33)
  - 40421 (Volume 34)
  - September, September 1-9 (Volume 35)
  - September, September 10-18 (Volume 36)
  - September, September 19-24 (Volume 37)
  - September Sermons, September 25-30 (Volume 38)
  - October, October 1-6 (Volume 39)
  - October, October 7-12 (Volume 40)
  - October, October 13-18 (Volume 41)
  - October Sermons, October 19-24 (Volume 42)
  - October 25-31 (Volume 43)
  - October 31 (Volume 44)
  - All Saints, November 1-6 (Volume 45)
  - November Sermons, November 7-12 (Volume 46)
  - November, November 13-18 (Volume 47)
  - November, November 19-24 (Volume 48)
  - Thanksgiving, November 25 - December 6 (Volume 49)
  - December, December 7-18 (Volume 50)
  - December, December 19-24 (Volume 51)
  - Christmas, December 25-31 (Volume 52)
  - Notes for Sermons and Addresses (Volume 53)
  - Poetry by Frederick Edwards (Volume 54)
  - Miscellaneous Collection of Frederick Trevenen Edwards (pre-World War I) (Volume 55)
  - Trevenen's Work: Poems & Prose, Vol. 1 (Volume 56)
  - Trevenen's Work: Poems & Prose, Vol. 2 (Volume 57)
  - Fifty letters concerning Rev. Frederick Edwards, 1915 (Volume 58)
  - January Journal Arcady (Box 1, Volume 59)
  - Natural Year, March (Box 1, Volume 60)
  - Natural Year, April (Box 1, Volume 61)
  - Natural Year, May (Box 2, Volume 62)
  - Natural Year, June (Box 2, Volume 63)
  - Natural Year, July (Box 2, Volume 64)
  - Natural Year, August (Box 3, Volume 65)
  - Natural Year, September (Box 3, Volume 66)
  - Natural Year, October (Box 3, Volume 67)
  - October Scrapbook (Box 4, Volume 68)
  - Natural Year, November (Box 4, Volume 69)
  - Natural Year, December (Box 4, Volume 70)
  - December Scrapbook (Box 5, Volume 71)
  - December Letters (Box 5, Volume 72)
  - Letters, 1915 (Box 5, Volume 73)
  - October 5 - Trinity (23) (Box 6, Volume 74)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures (Box 6, Volume 75)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures (Box 6, Volume 76)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1886-1887 (Box 7, Volume 77)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous (mainly 1880s) (Box 7, Volume 78)
  - Plays by Frederick Trevenen Edwards (1 of 2) (Box 9, Volume 79)
  - Plays by Frederick Trevenen Edwards (2 of 2) (Box 9, Volume 79)
  - Letters, 1915- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1916- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1917- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (1 of 2) (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1917- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (2 of 2) (Box 8)
  - Copies of Letters, 1917- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1918- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (1 of 2) (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1918- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (2 of 2) (Box 8)
  - Copies of Letters, 1918- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 8)
  - Letters Concerning Death of Frederick Trevenen Edwards, 1918-1921 (Box 8)
  - Copies of Letters Concerning Death of Frederick Trevenen Edwards, 1918 (Box 8)
  - Class Day Exercises, Columbia College- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 9)
  - Military Certificates- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Documents Concerning Death of Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 9)
  - Memorials and Newspaper Clippings- Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 9)
  - Miscellany: Fort Sheridan to Montfaucon: The War Letters of Frederick Trevenen Edwards (Box 9)
  - A Tribute to Rev. Frederick Edwards from the Choristers of St. Paul's Cathedral, Detroit, MI, December 1919 (Box 9)
  - A Symphony of Seasons: A Review of 'The Natural Year' by Frederick Edwards' by J. Howard Flower (Box 9)
  - The Radiant Array, painting by Alice R. Huger Smith (Box 9)